<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some reflections upon the author and licenser of a scandalous pamphlet called The missioners arts discover'd with the reply of A. Pullton to a challenge made him in a letter, prefix'd to the said pamphlet.</title>
            <author>Pulton, A. (Andrew), 1654-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56282</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12381687</idno>
  <idno type="VID">60788</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240949239</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8862</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12381687</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60788)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 820:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some reflections upon the author and licenser of a scandalous pamphlet called The missioners arts discover'd with the reply of A. Pullton to a challenge made him in a letter, prefix'd to the said pamphlet.</title>
                  <author>Pulton, A. (Andrew), 1654-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Mary Thompson for the author, and are to be sold by Matthew Turner ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Andrew Pulton.  Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>"The missionarie's arts discovered" is by William Wake.  Cf. BM.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Wake, William, 1657-1737. --  Missionarie's arts discovered.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60788:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60788:1"/>
            <p>SOME REFLECTIONS UPON THE <hi>Author and Licenser</hi> Of a Scandalous Pamphlet; called, <hi>The Missioners ARTS Discover'd.</hi> WITH THE REPLY OF A. PULTON TO A CHALLENGE Made Him in a LETTER Prefix'd to the said Pamphlet.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Qui semel verecundiae fines transierit, eum bene &amp; gnaviter oportet esse impudentem.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicero Lucceio 5 fam. Ep. 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>
                           <hi>With Allowance.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Mary Thompson</hi> for the Author, and are to be Sold by <hi>Matthew Turner</hi> at the <hi>Holy-Lamb</hi> in <hi>Holbourn,</hi> and <hi>John Lane</hi> at the <hi>Blew-Anchor</hi> in <hi>Wild-street,</hi> Anno Dom. 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:60788:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60788:2"/>
            <head>SOME REFLECTIONS UPON THE <hi>Anonymus Author</hi> AND THE LICENSER OF A Scandalous Pamphlet; CALLED, <hi>The Missioners Arts Discover'd,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT is well known, that there was one <hi>Needham</hi> that help'd (by the power of the Press) to bring <hi>Charles</hi> I. to the Scaffold; and labour'd hard to keep <hi>Charles</hi> II. from his Throne: Far be it from me to maintain that to have been his design, or that it is his present Namesakes, to imitate him: Yet the place he is Intrusted with, ought to make him Cautious, what Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences may attend the Scandalous Pamphlets, which are Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onsed by him to the Press. To write <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> upon a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunption of the Authors Honesty; is Remissness, if not Rashness: To pense, and yet to License Defamatory Libells, is inexcusable Malice: For he who allows of a Book, and abetts the Printing and Publishing of it becomes (though not a Legitimate Parent) a Step-Father at least hereof. So far as he is able, he Adopts it for his Own: So that if a Book prove a Trumpet to <hi>Rebellion,</hi> it is by his Breath it Sounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I shuld be apt to Censure my self for the freedom of this Address,</hi> (says my <hi>Anonyaus,</hi>) <hi>but it is certainly time to speak, when a Man in his Station,</hi> Who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60788:3"/>ought to advance in the Hearts of every Subject, an Obedience, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect and Esteem for his Prince; makes it his business, so far as in him lyes, to create in all a Contempt, Scorn, and Dis-respect of Him. To Ridicule even the Habit, Words, or Gesture of a Prince, is to lessen Him in the Minds of Those that Hear us: What then shall it be, to License Books stufft with Calumnies (not to say Blasphemies) against His Religion? To deliver to the People a Character of their King, as a Member of a <hi>Heathenish,</hi> Vain, Superstitious, Abominable <hi>Religion:</hi> What is it else, than to Imprint in them, a Notion of Him, as a <hi>Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish,</hi> Superstitious, Vain, and Abominable Man; and as Dr. <hi>Tenison,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Beverige</hi> teach. uncapable of Salvation, as having of <hi>Protestant</hi> become a <hi>Roman Catholick?</hi> Now what Honour, Allegiance, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect shall he retain for his Soveraign, who hath such an Abhorrence of the Man who is King? To Preach to us of Respecting His Majesty, and Despising most <hi>Calumniously</hi> his Religion; of Loving His Person, and <hi>unjustly</hi> Abhorring his Principles; is such a Phylosophical Barbarity, that it is only fit for the practice of <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants:</hi> These Principles being Abominated by all true <hi>Catholick Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</hi> Very many of this nature, have been Licensed by Mr. <hi>Needham,</hi> the most moderate of which would never have escap'd the Flames, had any <hi>Catholick</hi> presumed to Write and Vend the like Scurrilous Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations under a <hi>Protestant King</hi> against his Religion. But certainly none ever deserved it more, than a Pamphlet, called, <hi>The Missioners Arts Discovered,</hi> &amp;c. By the <hi>Imprimatur</hi> affixed thereunto, Mr. <hi>Needham</hi> approves of the Impious Calumny of <hi>Du Moulin,</hi> Charging the Murder of King <hi>Charles</hi> the First upon the <hi>Catholicks:</hi> Whereas he ought to have reflected, that for fear <hi>Catholicks</hi> might be in any Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to shew their Duty, or stir in His Majesties behalf, as was justly apprehended, it was specially Ordered by Parliament, that none should be allowed to come within 25 Miles of <hi>London</hi> during those <hi>black Days.</hi> And I challenge Mr. <hi>Needham,</hi> to Name those <hi>Catholicks,</hi> which by his <hi>Licensed</hi> Aspersions, he would have the World believe Interess'd therein. He approves moreover, and vends to the World, that the <hi>Catholicks</hi> never ventured to clear themselves of this detestable Crime imputed to them; which he cannot but know to be most false: That Lover of Truth, and Renowned Loyallist the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Castlemain,</hi> having done it more then 20 years ago in his Repl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Answer to the <hi>Catholicks</hi> Apology, to the eternal Confusion <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f that Impudent Calumniator; who when call'd to Account, had nothi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g else to say, than that he had heard <hi>Pim</hi> say so; a goodly Author or <hi>Protestants</hi> to build their Faith upon: But <hi>Moulin</hi> had a mind to ma<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a third to those two <hi>French</hi> Authors, one of which denyed, that the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> had ever Conquer'd <hi>France;</hi> and thesecond, that <hi>Francis</hi> the I had ever been taken Prisoner by the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60788:3"/>
            <p> Now our <hi>Anonymus,</hi> back'd with his <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> governs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self intirely by that Anti-Christian Maxime, <hi>Calumniare fortiter aliquid adhaerebit:</hi> And therefore I must be tax'd as a <hi>Slanderer,</hi> a <hi>Vender of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Falshood,</hi> with many such Charitable Characters, for returning, as the World must believe <hi>Rashly,</hi> the Charge of <hi>Disloyalty,</hi> and <hi>practising the Deposing Power,</hi> (when without Provocation Accus'd of it my self) upon our pretended Reformers. Now before an <hi>Imprimatur</hi> was given, Mr. <hi>Needham</hi> should in Justice have inform'd himself whether I had <hi>meerly,</hi> and <hi>rashly</hi> asserted this, as our <hi>Anonymus</hi> pretends, or <hi>prov'd</hi> it, as I did, by eight to or ten undenyable Instances, which he wisely passes in Silence.</p>
            <p>Before a Book be Licensed, it ought to be examined of what Credit the Authors are, which are alleadged for its support; of what Sincerity,<note place="margin">Account of the <hi>Conf.</hi> pag. ult.</note> of what Honesty. I shall take an instance from the very first passage of his over-grown Preface, to shew the Sincerity of his Authors, and his own Disingenuous Descant upon the Passage he Cavils at. He Ushers in then his Calumniatory Preface, with an Account of a Procession set forth by the <hi>Jesuits</hi> and their Students in <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> and takes it not from the <hi>true</hi> Relation published by the Authors, of which, <hi>Credite posteri,</hi> we must believe he could, (that is, he would) procure no Copy; for during the three Months which have pass'd since his Book was Licensed, he might have procured 30 if he had pleased; but <hi>Slander</hi> being what he evidently aimes at, and <hi>Truth</hi> what he hates, he made choice rather of a Scandalous Pamphlet, <hi>Very Rare,</hi> as he says, (for the Infamy of it) <hi>even in French,</hi> and thence he borrowes his Account.</p>
            <p>He passeth in Silence the real Devotion, extraordinary frequentation of Sacraments, and Edifying Sermons had on that occasion: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Students in Poetry exercis'd their vain in pious Fictions to Adorn some Pageants drest upon that occasion for a mixt and harmless Entertainment; he most Preposterously takes occasion thence to term this, <hi>A Consecrating the Pagan Gods to the Service of the Blessed Virgin;</hi> and offers it as a notion of that Worship the <hi>Jesuits</hi> (forsooth!) pay to the Mother of God. Now what can be imagin'd more opposite to the Sincerity of a Church-man, than to deliver to his Reader as a <hi>Catechistical Instruction,</hi> what every <hi>Grammar-Scholar</hi> understands to be the exercise of <hi>School-Boys?</hi> Who is so Sottishly Ignorant, except our Ignorant <hi>Anonymus,</hi> as not to understand, that a Poëtical Fiction is not to be taken in the rigour of Logick? And that Emblematical Symbols must of their own Nature <hi>be</hi> one thing, and <hi>represent</hi> another? O but there should be nothing Prophane in Sacred Processions; nothing that can draw off the Peoples Minds from Almighty God. Had this Reformer liv'd in King <hi>David</hi>'s days, how would he have been Scandaliz'd to hear Profane Instruments play before the Ark? He would have joyn'd
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60788:4"/>with the Religious <hi>Michol,</hi> and have accused the Servant of God of <hi>Heathenish</hi> Superstition, and contaminating the pure Rites of Gods Elect People, by introducing the <hi>Paganish</hi> Ceremonies of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> in Dancing before the <hi>Ark.</hi> He would have Quarrell'd with God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty for commanding the Portraits of Beasts to support the <hi>Lava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory;</hi> for what so unbeseeming, as to have Bestial Shapes cast before your Eyes, when you are intertaining your self with God? He would have Apostatiz'd from the <hi>Jewish</hi> Church, by reason of the number of her Ceremonies, Pomp, and State of the Temple; all which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of <hi>Paganism</hi> with our Reformer.</p>
            <p>Now what if the Intent of those <hi>Pageants</hi> was only to Assemble the People together, and so by an usual and pious Artifice, to invite them to more Serious and Religious Actions? What if somthing be allow'd to the more gross temper of that People, which in a more refin'd Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate might appear Exotick? But if you will needs have it Profane, keep then at Home in Gods name; you may remain a sound and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> without being oblig'd to approve of this, or t'other manner of Adorning Processions. But it is a strong Argument that he is depriv'd of Charity, and void of the Spirit of Christianity, who takes all things in the worst Sense, and Malitiously Interprets, what is Piously Design'd.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Anonymus</hi> would have done a great deal better to have kept his wandring Thoughts at Home, and Study'd how to excuse the Famous Procession of <hi>Westminster,</hi> when in <hi>Waller</hi>'s Reign our Blessed Redeemer was Burnt in <hi>Effigie,</hi> and <hi>Gill</hi> the Constable went Profanely about the Palace in <hi>Priests</hi> Habits, with the Tacite Applause of our Church of <hi>England</hi> Divines. I appeal to every unbyass'd Judgment, whether this was not a more Antichristian Action, than the shewing by a Poëtical Pageant, how the Mother of God is more worthy of Honour than the <hi>Paganish Deities?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have not singl'd out this Passage, as that which is most capable of discovering to you, our <hi>Anonymus</hi>'s Fraud and Malice, for most in-Instances of his Book are of the same Nature; but I took the first I met with, and will content my self at present, to remark, that the prime Authors on which he grounds his Charge against <hi>Catholicks;</hi> are infamous and defamatory Libels. Such as the <hi>Jesuits Morals,</hi> Burnt by a common Hangman in <hi>Paris; Arcana Societatis Jesu Secr. instruct.</hi> &amp;c. of the same stamp; <hi>Burnet</hi>'s <hi>Letters,</hi> inferior to neither for Slanderous Calumnies. with many more of equal Infamy. And I cannot but wonder, Mr. <hi>Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> should have so few Sparks of Loyalty in his Breast, as to License a Book (Traducing His Majesties Principles and Religion) chiefly suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Testimony. As though he who studiously has fallen from the Allegiance due to his Soveraign, and lyes under a most deserv'd
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60788:4"/>Outlawry from the Judgement of his own Country: Who imploys a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Endeavours to Vilify his Princes Person, and lessen his Interest at Home and Abroad; who supports by Publick Writing Infamous Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions: A person so Notorious for his Scurrillous Libelling and Impious Slanders, that he is call'd by the Loyal Party, <hi>The</hi> Oates <hi>of the</hi> Hague; who vents the Fictions of his own Malice as from the pretended Mouthes of this <hi>Courtier,</hi> or t'other <hi>Councellor:</hi> And we must believe all he Reports to be True, because <hi>Gilbert Burnet</hi> a Church of <hi>England</hi> Divine says it. It would be much more commendable for every Loyal Subject, to discredit such Stories, because <hi>Gilbert Burnet</hi> relates them.</p>
            <p>What can be so void of Sincerity, as to take the Notions of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctrine</hi> from its Sworn Enemies? What so Unreasonable and Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, as to reject the greatest Authorities, the most Sincere Historians, the Testimony of so many Ages, speaking in our Favour? And to believe with our <hi>Anonymus</hi> every <hi>Chamber-Maid, Old-Woman, Apostate, Libeller</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessing against us? To stile the Lives of so many thousand <hi>Romish</hi> Saints, <hi>Fanatick Enthusiasms?</hi> The most <hi>Authentick,</hi> and <hi>Juridical</hi> Examination of so many Miracles wrought in the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Church, <hi>Popish Impostures?</hi> The Conversion of so many Kingdoms rang'd by her under <hi>Christ</hi>'s Banner, effects of <hi>Ambitious Policy?</hi> And having thus with an <hi>Oxfordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Bellarmine Mentiris,</hi> given at once the Lye to all <hi>Catholick Antiquity,</hi> and Protested against all Authority, even that of <hi>Scripture,</hi> if it speak in <hi>Catholicks Favour:</hi> To open immediatly their Ears and Hearts, to <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Pamphlets,</hi> and <hi>Seditious Libels,</hi> if they contain any thing against them. Is this any thing less than studied Malice? Than <hi>Hearing not to Hear?</hi> And wittingly and willingly <hi>Sectari Mendacia,</hi> to love Lyes and the Father of them?</p>
            <p>There will not be wanting those who are Able and Willing to make better Reflections upon such <hi>Ʋnchristian</hi> Proceedings, than either my Talents or Leasure allow. I shall only Vindicate my self and my Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at present, with Proofs taken from what we have Experienc'd these last 12 years, which depend not upon <hi>History.</hi> The Charge of his fourth Chapter I shall argue with him <hi>Face to Face;</hi> and from the Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his <hi>own Eyes,</hi> Publish to the World the <hi>Remarks</hi> he is so Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of seeing.</p>
            <p>Far be it from me, in the mean time, to extend the Charge of Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty, or evil Practices of some Members of the Church of <hi>Engl.</hi> farther than the matter of Fact spreads them. Nor can it be doubted, but many thousand of that Persuasion have always been, and still are most Loyal and Faithful Subjects: And I could wish our <hi>Church of</hi> England <hi>Writers,</hi> were so favourable to <hi>Catholicks,</hi> as to draw no more under the <hi>Guilt</hi> of <hi>Treason,</hi> than the Law has found such. If six or eight Disloyal <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks;</hi> (not to mention who they were that drew them in) attempted a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60788:5"/>most-<hi>Ʋnchristian</hi> Practice upon the Life of His Sacred Majesty <hi>James</hi> I. Why must those Millions, who all the World over held, and still hold such <hi>Treasons</hi> in utter Detestation, be Arraign'd once a year at every <hi>Protestant Pulpit,</hi> as Guilty of the same <hi>Hellish Conspiracy?</hi> which was Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd to the King by an Honourable <hi>Catholick Peer.</hi> Nothing must ring in the Ears of the People, but <hi>Bloody-Papists,</hi> and <hi>Gun-Powder-Plots;</hi> as though their <hi>Fingers</hi> were <hi>Daggers,</hi> and their <hi>Veins</hi> Swell'd with <hi>Powder,</hi> instead of <hi>Blood:</hi> Whilst so many <hi>Exclusioners</hi> and <hi>Associators,</hi> though a thousand times more <hi>Numerous,</hi> and in their <hi>practices</hi> little less <hi>Villanous,</hi> and more <hi>Dangerous</hi> by reason of their Numbers, must pass for Loyal well-Principled Subjects. <hi>Catholicks</hi> Sins must always be <hi>Original, Protestants</hi> only <hi>Personal;</hi> what one <hi>Catholick</hi> does out of <hi>Perversness</hi> of Will, or <hi>Violence</hi> of <hi>Passion,</hi> is presently fix'd upon his <hi>Principles,</hi> charg'd upon his <hi>Religion;</hi> than which, what can be more inequitable?</p>
            <p>I never wrote a Paper with greater Aversion, than this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, nor us'd a Stile so contrary to my Temper; but in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversy I am Challenged to, no Body can do otherwise. Wherefore let the Guilt lye first at Dr. <hi>Tenison</hi>'s door; who, nothing provok'd, began this odious Debate; and then at his <hi>Seconds,</hi> who had less reason to <hi>rake</hi> up <hi>cover'd Embers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I answer our <hi>Anonymus</hi>'s Challenge, he must give me leave to expostulate with him concerning the <hi>Ʋnreasonableness</hi> of the same: The matter in debate between Dr. <hi>Tenison</hi> and my self, is, <hi>The Rule of Faith;</hi> the desiding of which question puts an end to all Controversy. I have four Months agoe demonstrated against the said Dr. the <hi>Insuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency</hi> of his <hi>Protestant Rule,</hi> and have all this while waited for his Answer, but in vain. Why has not his Second taken up the Cudgels for him? I Challenge him, and all his Abetters to Answer the said <hi>Defeat,</hi> Paragraph by Paragraph if he can. But he obliges me here to mind him of the usual Artifice of his Party; which is, when put to it by some undenyable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to fall a <hi>Bantering, Reviling, Defaming,</hi> and to throw all the Dirt they can (nor caring from what Kennel they gather it) in their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries Face.</p>
            <p>Now knowing of how little Edification and Profit such Brawls are, I have on design in my Answers to Dr. <hi>Tenison,</hi> let pass many virulent and injurious Reflections made by him, resolving to be drawn off by no particular Controversy from that question of questions, <hi>viz. What judge we are bound to hear in Controversies of Faith:</hi> And hence upon second thoughts, that I might oblige him to close upon this point, I resolved to transmit whatever else he hath amassed together in his <hi>Pulton Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered.</hi> However that the World may see I decline not any particular Debate, take my Answer to the Challenge as follows.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60788:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A. Pulton</hi>'s Reply to a <hi>Challenge</hi> sent him in a Letter Prefix'd to the said Pamphlet.</head>
               <p>IN the so much nois'd Conference held with Dr. <hi>Tenison</hi> on St. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi>'s day last, besides many other less charitable Asperssions which it pleas'd his Doctorship to Charge me with, nothing at all provok'd thereto by me; for a parting Blow, he thought fit to tax me with the being of a Religion, which is wholly destructive of all Honesty, Humane Conversation and Civil Life. <hi>Papists being by their Principles breakers of their Word,</hi> And that being a <hi>Jesuit,</hi> I held the <hi>Deposing-Power,</hi> my reply to each Charge, you have in the last pages of the Account of the <hi>Conference;</hi> and a small Reflection in my <hi>Remarks,</hi> pag. 31. 2. Where having said, to the latter, that <hi>Whatever some pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Men amongst the</hi> Catholicks <hi>had judged in the Theory, it was the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers who had reduced it to practice, and that besides those many instances alledg'd in the Account of the Conference</hi> (which our <hi>Anonymus</hi> confutes not, but wisely transmits,) <hi>I had many Remarks in store, which I would produce if farther provok'd:</hi> After 7 Months mature Consideration, our <hi>Noble Hero</hi> by himself, or some daring Second (<hi>Fergueson</hi> I conceive, or <hi>Burnet</hi>) has sent this dreadful <hi>Challenge</hi> in Frightful <hi>Characters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Anonymus, <hi>&amp;c. Do therefore here Challenge you</hi> Andrew Pulton Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit and Schoolmaster in the Savoy, <hi>as you would not appear a Slanderer and guilty of venting a most pernicious and notorious Falshood, as you value the Honour of your Church, and your own Reputation to publish those Remarks or else acknowledge you have Printed and Publish'd an Assertion, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard either to Truth or Modesty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Boldly Challeng d Gallant <hi>Anonymus:</hi> One would think that <hi>Andrew Pulton</hi> was certainly struck to the ground by the all Conquering <hi>Rodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montadoes</hi> of this <hi>Romantick Combatant;</hi> he must certainly be a man of Mettle, that dares brissel up against this Fiery-gill'd <hi>Hero. To appear a Slanderer,</hi> is a great Disgrace: <hi>To vent a pernicious and notorious Falshood;</hi> an immortal Infamy: <hi>To have no value for the Honour of my Church;</hi> an unparallel'd Ingratitude: <hi>Nor for my own Reputation,</hi> a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Stupidity: <hi>To publish an Assertion, without regard to Truth or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty;</hi> a more than <hi>Reformed</hi> Impudence.</p>
               <p>Poor <hi>Pulton,</hi> (wonder not that like a dubious Knight, I can't con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the Anxiety of my Panting-Heart) Poor <hi>Pulton,</hi> I say, had it not been a great deal better for thee, to let the Victorious Champion of St. <hi>Martins</hi> gather with Glory the Spoils of his Conquest, and commit in <hi>Brazen Plates</hi> to Postery the Memory of his Trophyes, rais'd on the Defeat of <hi>Savoy-Jesuits,</hi> Lady St. <hi>Johns Jesuit,</hi> and Lady St. <hi>Johns Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits,</hi> suppos'd fellow <hi>Jesuit,</hi> and Yellow Peruke <hi>Jesuits;</hi> and Lord
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60788:6"/>knows how many <hi>Jesuits</hi> scatter'd in the Crowd, besides others as <hi>good</hi> as <hi>Jesuits,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies before my <hi>Remarks.</hi>
                  </note> let them be eight, ten, fifteen, fifty, (for all these num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers have had their Abetters) than by Imprudently discovering the Shamme, thus to expose thy self to the fury of an enrag'd Conqueror? Although the World had remain'd in the Belief that you came with a <hi>Train of eight or ten Abetters, a Band of Bully Scholars,</hi> marching under ground with their <hi>Black-Bills,</hi> beside the foresaid number of <hi>Invisible Jesuits:</hi> It would have been no disgrace though so back'd, to be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated by a <hi>Church of</hi> England <hi>Divine:</hi> The meanest of which is <hi>Wiser</hi> than <hi>Eleven Ages</hi> past, and bids defyance to <hi>as many General Councils.</hi> and setteth at nought <hi>Eleven thousand Romish Divines.</hi> You had done much wiser, had you quietly sat down, and let things take their course; it had been but the undergoing the Charge of a <hi>Falsifier, A Man who has not common skill in History, a Violator of the Holy-day, a bringer in of Foreign Jurisdiction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nison</hi>'s ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Confer.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>a Teacher of the Deposing-Power,</hi> a Catechist of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, who instructs his Hearers <hi>to Lye, to be idle, Ʋneasie to Others, a Corrupter of Morals, a Person obliged by his Principles to break his Word.</hi> Nay, you should have esteem'd it a Happiness that you came off no worse; and that you fell into the Hands of a man, <hi>Who never endamag'd any one so far, as the hurting a Hair of his Head for Religion.</hi> Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, if you had considered, how many of your <hi>Fellow-Jesuits</hi> died late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Banishment, rotted in Goals, and that no less, than Eight were so lately Hanged, Drawn, and Quarter'd; three Kingdoms brought almost to Destruction; and His present Majesty, the best of Monarchs, three times obliged to quit His Countrey, to yeild to the All-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Breath of Two Church of <hi>England</hi> Divines, back'd by the godly Assistance of their <hi>Pulpit-Brethren,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tong.</hi> and Dr. <hi>Oates.</hi>
                  </note> who pointed out to the People a <hi>New Saviour,</hi> and never Retracted, as we know, their Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy.</p>
               <p>Considering all this, I say, had it not been more advisable for you, to shake your Ears peaceably at Home; than by rash Scribling to be thus publickly Disgraced, and Rot in Print? Rot, I say, in Print for <hi>venting so bold a Slander, tending to expose the Pure Churches of Christ, as Enemies to their Sovereigns, and so render them Odious to those</hi> (Their present Majesties) <hi>from whom they have all imaginable reason to expect Protection, as from Nursing Fathers,</hi> says our <hi>Anonymus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For what I beseech you so endearing, as to see a Loyal Church of <hi>England</hi> Prince,<note place="margin">D. of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi>
                  </note> so True to his <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and Zealous for the <hi>pure Church</hi> of Christ, as to give Himself the Trouble of crossing the Seas, with three Ships of <hi>Protestant Subjects,</hi> and joyn'd by Thousands of the same Zeal and Spirit, to undertake a dangerous Progress into the Heart of the Kingdom, with intention to shew his Love to the Crown; and for his Reward to loose his Loyal Head on <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> to the great Disappointment of his <hi>Spiritual Guides,</hi> D. <hi>T.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60788:6"/>
               <p> Who so far from being <hi>Abetters of the Deposing Power,</hi> or <hi>Enemies to their Sovereign,</hi> as they who in three Parliaments, out of Tenderness to the Heir Apparent, past <hi>An Act for securing of the</hi> Protestant Religion, <hi>by Disabling</hi> James <hi>Duke of</hi> York <hi>to Inherit the Imperial Crown of</hi> England, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and the Dominions and Territories thereunto belonging.</hi> What I say so Obliging, so Charming, so Loyal, as Devoutly to Vote in the Lord? (five Reverend Bishops labouring notably in the Cause:) <hi>Be it Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, by and with the Advice and Consent of the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and the Commons in this present Parliament Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by the Authority of the same: That the said</hi> James <hi>Duke of</hi> York <hi>shall be, and is by the Authority of the same excluded, and made for ever uncapable to Inherit, Possess, or enjoy the Imperial Crown of this Realm — And be it farther Enacted — That if the said</hi> James <hi>Duke of</hi> York <hi>shall at any time hereafter, Challenge, Claim, or Attempt — any Dominion, Power or Authority, within the said King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms — as King or Chief Magistrate of the same; that then he the said</hi> James <hi>Duke of</hi> York — <hi>Shall be deemed and adjudged guilty of High Treason, and shall suffer the Pains and Penalties, as in Cases of Treason And be it further Enacted — That the said</hi> James <hi>Duke of</hi> York <hi>shall not at any time, from and after the</hi> 5 <hi>of</hi> October 1680. <hi>return, or come into, or within any of the Kingdoms or Dominions aforesaid</hi> —</p>
               <p>Now considering these signal Remonstrances of Loyalty, not to have proceeded from a <hi>Fleeting</hi> tenderness of Affection, but to be the effect of a <hi>Forethought</hi> and <hi>Imbred</hi> Allegiance, <hi>Reiterated</hi> by so many <hi>Different</hi> Members Assembled in so many <hi>Different</hi> Parliaments from <hi>all</hi> Parts of the Kingdom, and delivering the <hi>Judgement</hi> of their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Teachers</hi> in their <hi>Respective Counties,</hi> (there being <hi>very few</hi> Ch. of <hi>England</hi> Divines, who shewed a <hi>Dislike</hi> of what was transacting in that <hi>Grand Assembly:</hi>) Who, I say, considering all this, dare <hi>be so bold as to expose the Members of the pure Church of</hi> England, <hi>as Enemies to their Sovereign, or Abetters of the Deposing Power?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the <hi>Papists</hi> boast that not one of their Church ever drew his Sword against their Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> I, though of a different Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from theirs: Yet they are the <hi>Protestant Subjects who have all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable Reason to expect Protection from</hi> James <hi>the</hi> II. (whom God long preserve) <hi>as from d' Nursing-Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that you may not believe, that the chief Representatives of the Nation were only Animated by these <hi>Loyal Spirits,</hi> the Numerous Rolls of <hi>Associators</hi> demonstrate moreover, an Union of Will and Judgement in many Thousands, and how rare it is to find a <hi>Protestant Abetter of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60788:7"/>the Deposing-power,</hi> witness the following Act of <hi>Abhorrence,</hi> Subscribed by so many <hi>men worthy</hi> of their Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do in the presence of God solemnly Promise, Vow, and Protest to maintain &amp; Defend to the utmost of my Powee with my Person and Estate the</hi> True Protestant Religion — <hi>And that I will never Consent that</hi> James <hi>Duke of</hi> York, <hi>or any other who is, or hath been a</hi> Papist — <hi>Be admitted to the Succession of the Crown of</hi> England; <hi>but by all Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Means, and by force of Arms, if need so require — to Subdue, Expel and Destroy Him, if he come into</hi> England.</p>
               <p>Nor can it be pretended that this was a <hi>Test of the Dissenters Loyalty,</hi> and not of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> since it was Read with Applause in Parliament: Nor have I yet been able to hear of a Church of <hi>England</hi> Divine, who in that Conjuncture, either Preach'd, or wrote against it, by which their Silence, they undoubtedly Consented to it, and declar'd their good liking of it: For had they been of a contrary Judgement, and esteem'd it <hi>Ʋnjust, Illegal</hi> or <hi>Disloyal</hi> to put by, the immediat Heir upon a meer acount of <hi>Religion;</hi> they ought, being the <hi>Directors</hi> and <hi>Gov rnours</hi> of the Peoples Consciences to have declared to them the <hi>Disloyalty</hi> and <hi>Injustice</hi> of such Proceedings.</p>
               <p>Nor did our <hi>Protestant Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>abhorrence of that deposing</hi> Power, extend it self only to the immediate Heir, but the Person of their then present Sovereign. How much would some of the Godly Asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates have made on his late Majesty at <hi>Rye-house</hi> (to omit other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrances of like kindness,) had Heaven seconded their Zeal. And had that moderate Prince had but a little more good nature to <hi>part with his Militia for forty days, till the Parliament had settled the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> they would perhaps have made him as glorious a King, and raised him as high as his most excellent Father. They would have so enriched him, that by publick Vote no man should lend him a Penny.</p>
               <p>Her Majesty the Queen Dowager (who like the best of Christians is most grateful for it) did particularly feel the influence of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Loyalty,</hi> while they encouraged the <hi>Divine Oaten Mouth</hi> of their <hi>Church,</hi> to swear against her, <hi>Nov.</hi> 26. 29. 1679. whereas but the 30th of <hi>October</hi> before, the said <hi>true Church of</hi> England <hi>Doctor</hi> had deposed upon <hi>Oath</hi> he had no other Persons to accuse then those men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in his Narrative.<note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Hawkins</hi> Narrative, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> And that <hi>in the mouth of two Witnesses all Truth might stand,</hi> the same <hi>Party</hi> encouraged Mr. <hi>Fitz-Harris</hi> to accuse Her said Majesty of High Treason. Now having all these undoubted marks of <hi>Protestant Loyalty</hi> in my Eye, without having recourse to any Notes of History, it is a subject of astonishment, how it should come into my Head to charge any Members of <hi>that pure Church of Christ, as Enemies to their Sovereigns, or abetters of the deposing Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60788:7"/>
               <p> Nor can it be objected that these <hi>Loyal Spirits</hi> are now extinct, or that any Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are <hi>fallen,</hi> or <hi>falling</hi> from their Obedience. My Lord of <hi>L.</hi> first gave Demonstrations with what <hi>Promptitude</hi> and <hi>Alacrity</hi> a Church of <hi>England-man may</hi> at lest pay his Submission to the Orders of His Majesty, whom he has bound himself by so many <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Tests</hi> to obey. The Fellows of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge have made appear to the world, how forward they were in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Example to both Universities, of the Obedience due to our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns most <hi>Legal</hi> and <hi>Positive Mandates.</hi> How ought the People to bless God for having such <hi>Mirrours of reformed Obedience</hi> before their Eyes? But nothing ever gave a more Conspicuous Argument of <hi>an unshaken Allegiance,</hi> and <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> than the so much celebrated forwardness of some Church of <hi>England</hi> Prelates, in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering according to their Rubrick (as commanded) his Majesties most gracious Declaration to be read to the People; <hi>who over-gave to</hi> Caesar <hi>his due more than they,</hi> who <hi>raise</hi> themselves above the 12 <hi>Judges</hi> of the Land, and <hi>rescind</hi> by a <hi>Definitive</hi> Vote, the <hi>Declaration</hi> of the <hi>Highest standing Court?</hi> What so <hi>Loyal,</hi> as, with an <hi>humble Submission,</hi> to tell His Majesty, that what He had Commanded, <hi>by the Ʋnanimous consent of His most Honourable Privy-Council, guided by the unquestionable Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Legal and only present Interpreters of the Law,</hi> was Illegal? May not the <hi>Crown</hi> now be assured of all <hi>Support</hi> from such <hi>Pillars</hi> of the Protestant Church? Although <hi>Charles</hi> I. the meekest of Princes, laid down his Head in defence of his Bishops, yet now the Scene is changed, and they are the Church of <hi>England Divines</hi> who are ready <hi>to lay down theirs,</hi> to maintain His present Majesties Prerogative.</p>
               <p>But to be serious in so weighty a matter; what malignant effects must such a <hi>palbable Disobedience</hi> produce, in all those thousands who take <hi>the Sense of the Law,</hi> not from the lawful Judges, but their <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters Lips?</hi> May not every Pettifogger from the <hi>example of his Pastor,</hi> having read any of his Majesties Declarations, and Commands, say; I can't comply with it, it is against Law: I won't act as Justice of the Peace, or in any other Commission for His Majesty, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Tests;</hi> for <hi>my Minister tells me,</hi> that the Judges have all pronounced contrary to Law, in favour of the Prerogative. <hi>My</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is, that His Majesty's Pretension to the Dispensing Power is Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal. And if this come to pass, who will be deemed the Authors of such <hi>Seditious</hi> and <hi>Rebellious</hi> Practises?</p>
               <p>Will not the World have reason to think, that the so much <hi>boasted of Church</hi> of <hi>England Loyalty</hi> is like to prove little else in the root, than <hi>Self-love</hi> and <hi>Interest?</hi> And that <hi>some</hi> of them so long only pretend to <hi>Loyalty,</hi> as there is nothing to be got by being <hi>otherwise?</hi> for having all the Ecclesiastical livings in their hands, and bearing all the charges in Church and State, what should move them to Disloyalty? But no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60788:8"/>sooner shall their <hi>fellow Creatures</hi> be allowed to breath <hi>with freedom</hi> the common Air; their <hi>fellow Subjects</hi> to share in their <hi>Sovereigns</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Grace and Protection; their <hi>fellow Christians</hi> to enjoy some small <hi>Liberty</hi> of Religious Worship; but presently the Kingdom must be alarmed, the Publick Peace disturbed, the <hi>Sentence</hi> of the Judges, the Order of Council, and His Majesties <hi>express Will, grounded upon,</hi> and <hi>guided by both,</hi> termed to his Face Illegal?</p>
               <p>But I forget my self, my <hi>Anonymus</hi> warns me that such Discourses which reflect upon the Disloyalty of some of the Party,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 69.</note> may be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by ill Consequences, and that it is the way <hi>to provoke them to some undecent Carriage.</hi> As tho' he would say, <hi>tell</hi> us not of our <hi>Faults,</hi> for if you do we shall <hi>commit</hi> the <hi>same</hi> again. If so small a provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be necessary to <hi>shake the Loyalty</hi> of a Church of <hi>England</hi> Divine, how shall he blame, by that Principle, the want of it in some Dissenters, whom the <hi>tenderness</hi> of that Church by Canabal Laws, unconscionable Extortions, and violent Oppressions, hath, as it were, <hi>obliged</hi> to those Practices they had never thought of, under a moderate Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Never thought of, I say, under a moderate Government; for who ever gave less <hi>disturbance</hi> to the Publick Peace, shewed greater Demonstrations of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Gratitude</hi> to their <hi>Prince,</hi> than the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters have <hi>unanimously</hi> done, since his Majesties Gracious Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence? Which had the tenderness of the Church of <hi>England</hi> allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be extended sooner upon them, had begot, unquestionably a most firm sense of Loyalty in the hearts of some who seemed most to want it. For if the <hi>meer minding</hi> a Church of <hi>England-man</hi> of the Dis-loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of <hi>some</hi> of that Perswasion, be enough to thrust him upon the <hi>like Practices?</hi> If an <hi>equal temper</hi> shewed by a Prince, towards those who are <hi>equally</hi> his Subjects, without prejudicing any Church of <hi>England<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Liberty</hi> or <hi>Property,</hi> hath produced in <hi>many</hi> of them, as <hi>appears,</hi> such Marks of Disloyalty, and Contempt of Sovereignty; what may we think they would do, what Measures would they take, what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions, if they should be treated (which Heaven avert) as they have treated their fellow Subjects?</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Pen</hi> in his <hi>Good advice, pag.</hi> 57. giving account only of what falls under our own knowledge, has computed no less than fifteen thousand Families ruined since the late Kings Restauration, and more than five thousand Persons dead under Bonds, for matter of meer Conscience. Now tho' I question not but the <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> of <hi>many</hi> a Loyal <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> would stand the proof of such <hi>usage;</hi> yet it is no rash Judgment to think some grains of allowance would be requisite to several of them. Wherefore if they are unwilling to be provoked to <hi>Ʋndecent Actions,</hi> why are they so forward in <hi>Provoking</hi> others, by declaring themselves such <hi>Abetters</hi> of the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> the <hi>true</hi> Source and Fountain of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion? Let the meek-hearted Church of <hi>England-men</hi> learn to have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60788:8"/>Bowels of Compassion for the dissenting Parties, and the World will soon experience the Dissenters Loyalty to their Prince, to <hi>vye</hi> with, and perhaps <hi>out-do</hi> that of some Members of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ead <hi>Episcopacy</hi> been <hi>Voted</hi> down, (after His late Majesties Restaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) as it was in a fair way to be; the House of Commons having pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the Vote, and the House of Lords (had it not been for the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peers) joyning with them, let the World imagine how <hi>the Party</hi> would have resented it? What Disloyalty would, <hi>being Persecuted,</hi> have begot in them, whose Loyalty totters upon account they are refused the Priviledge of <hi>Persecuting</hi> others? If the not being able to <hi>make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers miserable</hi> hath such effects, what would <hi>the being miserable them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves</hi> drive them upon? If while they are in a most peaceable possession of <hi>every</hi> Church and Chappel in the Kingdom, that ever belonged to them, even that of His Sacred Majesties own Palace, they raise such <hi>Clamours,</hi> as, we <hi>daily</hi> hear, are filled with those <hi>unjust Surmises</hi> and <hi>Jealousies,</hi> and amuse the People with those <hi>Groundless Frights</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions,</hi> which <hi>all the World</hi> is witness of, what <hi>Temper</hi> would they shew, what <hi>Heat,</hi> (let me not say <hi>Fury</hi>) were the Dissenters allowed the liberty of <hi>Retaliation,</hi> and returning the <hi>Ʋsage</hi> upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> she has hitherto exercised towards them.</p>
               <p>I am as unwilling to remain upon this odious Subject, as I was averse from entring upon it, but being thus provok'd by a Church of <hi>England</hi> Man, and oblig'd to produce to the World all the <hi>Remarks I have made of Reformers Disloyalty;</hi> I let him know by these, that I accept his <hi>Challenge.</hi> I have at present only instanced the last 12 years, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected only on the Practices and Principles of <hi>some</hi> Church of <hi>England<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> let our <hi>Anonymus</hi> produce from <hi>publick Acts,</hi> or <hi>Credible Authors,</hi> the like Arguments of <hi>Catholicks</hi> Disloyal Principles and Practices, during this same space of time; nor shall I confine him to the narrow bounds of our own Kingdom, but freely allow him the whole Circumference of the Universe; and if he can, let him make appear to the World, that <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> now living <hi>all the World over,</hi> have either, in their <hi>Practices</hi> appear'd such <hi>Enemies to their Sovereigns;</hi> or in their <hi>Pinciples,</hi> such <hi>Abetters of the Deposing-power;</hi> as some of the Church of <hi>England<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> have shew'd themselves to be.</p>
               <p>As for what belongs to the Dead, to the Practices and Principles of <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> on one side, and the <hi>Pretended Reformers</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: I am so far from declining the Debate of each Parties Loyalty, or Retracting what I said in the <hi>Conference,</hi> that I receive with a most willing Mind the Challenge. <hi>I do therefore here require you</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonymus, <hi>that you meet me in what Place you think sit, with two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses and no more, of what condition you please, and an</hi> Amanuensis, <hi>some day before the Tenth of</hi> July <hi>following in this present year</hi> 1688. <hi>Giving me three days warning, least I should not be at Home, or be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60788:9"/>otherwise engag'd; having accordingly met, where, and when you shall appoint; we will presently repair to a Library, and from ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd</hi> Histories, <hi>and Credible</hi> Authors <hi>put to the Test the</hi> Remarks, <hi>we both pretend to have made. I will make good my Assertion,</hi> viz. That the pretended <hi>Reformers</hi> have Depos'd, and endeavour'd to Depose more <hi>Princes</hi> in the space of a 150 years, than the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> have on the like account of Religion since Christs time. <hi>You to are prove,</hi> That the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> have Depos'd, and endeavour'd to Depose, more than the <hi>Reformers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 77.</note> in the same space of this last 150 years. <hi>You are moreover to make out,</hi> 65 Rebellions rais'd, and Paracides com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon great Princes in about one hundred and sixty years, and eighty two <hi>Bulls, Indulgences,</hi> and <hi>Supplies</hi> of the <hi>Popes</hi> for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of those <hi>Treasons,</hi> besides an infinite number of Horrid Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies. <hi>Moreover,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 79.</note> That the <hi>Popes</hi> Power in that point (<hi>of Deposing Princes,</hi> &amp;c.) was Universally Reliev'd, as a matter of Faith in that Church for near five hundred years.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All which being Examin'd before Witnesses, and the Truth of each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular searched into from the respective credible Authors; shall be written down by two</hi> Amanuenses, <hi>and the Copies being Compar'd and Exchang'd, shall be Seal'd up, and sent to the Press, without any Change or Alteration; and being Printed, shall be again compared before the same Witnesses with the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals, and being in this manner made publick, we will leave to the World to judge. Whether you Mr.</hi> Anonymus, <hi>or I appear a Slanderer, and guilty of venting most pernicious and notorious Falsbood, without regard to Truth or Modesty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have desir'd <hi>You</hi> to appoint a place to meet in, because I know not who you Are, nor where you Live; nor will I oblige you to a place of my nominating, least you might suspect, some Fraud; and to require you should take me up at our <hi>Schools,</hi> I cannot perswade my self you dare venture your Person, among Men whom you represent to the World, to be of such <hi>Bloody, Murthering Principles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have chose this method of a <hi>publick Conference,</hi> and <hi>mutual Parley,</hi> as the only Expedient to avoid all suspition of false Quotations, and Fraud. As also, that the matter of Fact being Contested on each side, the World may know for the future, whether to Address themselves in a matter of this Concern; and how much, or how little, is true of what the <hi>Pulpits</hi> have Ecchoed out, for so many years, setting forth the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> to the People under the most Bloody and Horrid Shape, the most enraged fury could invent. I do here solemnly engage, that if you Mr. <hi>Anonymus</hi> can make good your Charge against <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks;</hi> and prove your self any thing less, than a <hi>Calumnious Impostor,</hi> to become upon the Spot your <hi>Proselite.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:60788:9"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>